Let's continue with our next programming assignment where you'll actually
さあ プログラミングの 次の課題です ここでは LiDARの測定値を
build a Kalman filter that can take in lidar measurements and
取り込む カルマンフィルターを 作成して 歩行者を 2Dで
track a pedestrian in 2D.
追跡します
That's pretty cool.
かなり 便利ですよね
The State Vector of a pedestrian is described by px py position
歩行者の 状態ベクターを 位置(px, py) と 速度(vx, vy)で
vx vy velocity.
表します
I will give you some starter code, but
スターターコードを 用意したので
I want you to set out the rest of the Kalman filter variables.
カルマンフィルター変数の 残りを 自分で 設定してください
This time, the code is structured into three main parts, a KalmanFilter class,
今回は コードが 3つの部分に 分かれています  KalmanFilterクラスと
a Tracking class, and a MeasurementPackage class.
Trackingクラス そして MeasurementPackageクラスです
Here I have the KalmanFilter class, the cpp file and
ここに KalmanFilterクラス それから cppファイルと
the corresponding header file.
対応するヘッダーファイルが あります
This is what you've already coded but the whole KalmanFilter code including
これは 皆さんが 作成したコードですが KalmanFilterコード全体と 予測関数 そして
its predict and update functions is now decoupled from the tracking logic.
更新関数が Trackingロジックから 切り離されています
We also have a Tracking class where we actually create and
Trackingクラスもあり ここでは 実際に KalmanFilterオブジェクトを
use a KalmanFilter object.
作成して 使用します
For this quiz, you're going to modify F and Q matrices
このクイズでは 前の測定から 現在の測定までの
according to the elapsed time between the current and previous measurement.
経過時間に従って F行列と Q行列を 変更します
You can do so inside the process measurement function.
これは process_measurements関数の 内部で 実行できます
Afterwards, your code should call the KalmanFilter predict and
その後 コードで KalmanFilterの 予測関数と 更新関数を
update functions.
呼び出します
Just keep in mind that all the KalmanFilter matrices,
忘れないで ほしいのは Kalman Filterの行列や
as well as the predict update functions are members of the kf_ object.
予測関数 そして更新関数が すべて kfオブジェクトの メンバーであることです
There is a big difference between this and previous programming assignment.
前のプログラミング問題と この問題には 大きな違いがあります
Here, we don't process the entire list of measurements, but
ここでは 一連の測定値を すべて 処理するのではなく
rather the most recent measurement.
最新の測定値だけを 処理します
We are simulating a more realistic scenario where the process measurement
これは より現実的な シナリオの シミュレーションであり このシナリオでは
function is called every time we receive new data from a given sensor which,
センサーから 新しいデータが 届くたびに process_measurement関数が 呼び出されます
in this case, is only from a laser scanner.
この例では センサーとして レーザースキャナーだけを 使います
Also, the sensor data is organized in package objects now.
また ここではセンサーデータが パッケージオブジェクトとして 整理されます
These measurement packages are passed as an argument to the process measurement
これらの測定値パッケージは 引数として process_measurement関数に
function.
渡されます
As you see here,
ここで わかるとおり
the package properties are grouped into MeasurementPackage class.
パッケージプロパティは MeasurementPackageクラスに まとめられています
So this class is composed of a timestamp_ variable,
このクラスの 構成要素のうち タイムスタンプ変数は
which is a point in time where the measurement was created by a sensor and
センサーによって 測定値が作成された 時点を 示し
an enum variable called SensorType with two options, LASER and RADAR.
列挙型変数の SensorTypeは LASERと RADARの オプションを 持ちます
This is not important right now, as you will only see laser measurement.
これは 今は 重要ではありません レーザーの 測定値だけを 使うからです
And there is also vector variable with most recent raw measurements.
それから 最新の 生の測定値を持つ ベクター変数もあります
Specifically, if MeasurementPackage comes from a laser sensor,
特に 測定値パッケージが レーザーセンサーから 来る場合は
then the raw_measurements_ vector will contain just observed x and y position.
生測定値のベクターには 観測された x位置と y位置だけが 含まれます
And here is an example of retrieving my data from MeasurementPackage.
そして これは 測定パッケージから データを 読み取る例です
You'll see the x measurement, the y measurement and the timestamp.
xの測定値 yの測定値 そして タイムスタンプが あります
And if we print out these values, the result would be something like this.
これらの値を 出力すると 結果は こんな感じになります
The x position, the y position and the timestamp.
x位置と y位置と タイムスタンプです
The big number assigned to the timestamp variable,
タイムスタンプ変数に 割り当てられた 大きな値は
is the number of microseconds that have elapsed since Thursday, January 1,
1970年1月1日（木）からの 経過時間を マイクロ秒で
1970 which obviously always increases.
表したもので 当然ながら 常に増加します
I would like to point out that in this programing assignment the tracking code
ここで 指摘したいのは この課題の Trackingコードが
will first call the predict function and then measurement update function.
まず 予測関数を 呼び出し その後で 更新関数を 呼び出すことです
And that is because our prediction depends on the elapsed time between
これは 予測が 2つの 測定値の間の 経過時間に 依存し
two measurements, and the time is not fixed anymore.
その時間が 固定されていないためです
So we can predict our state only after next observation timestamp is available.
そのため 状態を予測するためには 次の観測タイムスタンプを 取得する必要があります
Basically we have to wait for the next process measurement call, and
基本的には process_measurementの 次回の呼び出しを 待ってから
then to apply the prediction, right before the next measurement update.
予測を 適用し その直後に 次の測定値更新が 行われます
The first process measurement call will just initialize the state position with
process_measurementの 最初の 呼び出しは 状態の位置を xと yの
the first x and y measurement and the state velocity vx,
最初の測定値で 初期化し 状態の 速度の vy vxを 0で 初期化します
vy with 0, assuming we don't know the initial velocity and that's it.
これは 初期速度が 不明であると 仮定しています これで 終わりです
Remember if you're having trouble,
何か わからないときは
the steps you need to take are written as a comment in the code.
コードのコメントを 見れば 指示が 書いてあります
Good luck.
がんばってください